RG 003, New London County, County Court Papers By Subject
Connecticut State Library
The final series, Travel, fills Boxes 91-104 and contains materials on three subjects - highways, tavern licenses, and annual financial reports of three corporations. The largest quantity of papers in Travel concern the subjects of building, erecting or removing gates across, changing the routes of, repairing, or discontinuing highways. The county court dealt with petitions for roads built and maintained by towns, although public highways could traverse several towns, while the General Assembly had jurisdiction over turnpikes charging tolls.
The transportation of goods, services, and people along country roads, public highways, turnpikes, and on bodies of water like the Thames and Connecticut Rivers was a matter of great public importance and the county court devoted considerable attention to it. In addition, these documents provide much useful information on where people lived in relationship to one another. To cite one example, the county court heard a petition from James Harris in 1726 on the necessity of a country road between Lyme and Colchester to begin,
"Some where between ye Dwelling house of yr memorialist & ye Dwelling house of James harris Junr & from thnce through ye Lands of sd memorialist to Coll Browns farme on which mr Gallusia Lives... through ye Lands of ye sd Brown to New London Country Road which Goes from N: L: town to Capt. Latimers farme at ye Edge of New London bounds Westward.. ."42
The appointment of tavern keepers, innholders, or keepers of houses of public entertainment marked another responsibility of the county court. Tavern keepers were nominated at special meetings held on the first Monday in January of each year devoted exclusively to this duty. "At a Meeting of the Civil Authority, Selectmen, Constables, and Grandjurymen of the Town of Lyme... the following Persons were nominated to Keep Houses of Publick Entertainment... the Year Ensuing."43 The county court generally confirmed the nominees at their June session. Tavern keepers were often men of considerable importance in their communities during the eighteenth century, but in the first half of the nineteenth century their numbers declined, as did their status in their towns. By the 1830s, the court began to receive petitions and remonstrances from those opposing the liquor trade. One such remonstrance signed by fifty-six persons from the Jewett City section of Griswold asserted that "Griswold like many other towns... for some year past [has been] cursed with rum selling taverners of the very worst description who have done much directly or indirectly to disturb the peace and corrupt the morals of the community."44
The county court also received annual financial reports from three corporate entities. The first turnpike in New England and the second in the United States was the Mohegan Turnpike. Travel contains annual financial records for the turnpike for most of the years between 1792 and 1852, when the tollgate was abolished.45 The subseries contains financial accounts of the Niantic Bridge Company for about half of the period between 1797 and 1848 and those for the Norwich Channel Company, 1810-25.46
Endnotes
4Papers by Subject, Admissions to the Bar, Box 1, folder 1. Signers of the petition were Jedidiah Elderkin, George Richards, George Dorr, Samuel Huntington, Elisha Paine, John Elderkin, Richard Law, John Shipman, Samuel Holden Parsons, Elisha Fitch, Stephen Babcock, Benjamin Huntington, Nathaniel Minor, Marvin Wait, and William Coit. See page 12 for an image of this application.
5Ibid, Admissions to the Bar, Box 1, folder 2.
6See, for example, Trials, Vol. 24, Nov. 1763-Dec. 1768, June 1766 for William Coit (New London) and June 1768 for Solomon Kellog (Colchester).
7A reference to the British raid on New London and Groton led by Benedict Arnold. Ibid, Appointment of Officers, Box 1, folder 11. William Noyes of Lyme was appointed County Treasurer and Winthrop Saltonstall of New London retained his position as County Clerk.
8Additional cases are found scattered throughout Files.
9Papers by Subject, Conservators and Guardians, Johnson, Mrs. Anne, Box 5, folder 1.
10Ibid, Conservators and Guardians, Perkins, Dr. Abisha, Box 6, folder 5.
11Ibid, Conservators and Guardians, Bishop, Nathaniel, Box 2, folder 19.
12Ibid, Conservators and Guardians, Atwell, Richard, Box 2, folder 16.
13Ibid, Conservators and Guardians, Halsey, Thomas, Box 4, folder 11.
14Ibid, Conservators and Guardians, Ely, Richard, Box 4, folder 5.
15Ibid, Costs, June 1705, Box 7, folder 11.
16Ibid, Costs, Nov. 1719, Box 9, folder 4.
17Ibid, Costs, June 1732, Box 12, folder 20
18Ibid, Costs, June 1742, Box 16, folder 18
19These lists of prisoners and the expenses they incurred while in jail include the names of males and females, whites, Indians, and Negroes.
20An execution is the act or carrying out of a court order. Black's Law Dictionary, 8th ed., 609.
21Papers by Subject, Executions, John Waterman, Jr. v. Joseph Tracy, 1726, Box 29, folder 15.
22Ibid, Executions, Samuel Bishop v. Nathaniel Beckwith, 1763, Box 43, folder 16.
23Ibid, Executions, 1762, Box 45, folder 13.
24Ibid, Executions, 1754, Box 41, folder 12.
25Ibid, Executions, 1812, Box 61, folder 6.
26Jarvis Means Morse, A Neglected Period of Connecticut's History 1818-1850 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1933), 254-55.
27NLCC, Papers by Subject: Executions, 1846, Box 70, folder 2.
28For regulations concerning the choosing and summoning of jurors to serve as jury men at the county and superior courts, see, The Public Statute Laws of the State of Connecticut (Hartford: Printed by Hudson and Goodwin, 1808), 426-29.
29Papers by Subject, Jurors, Bozrah, Box 73, folder 1.
30Ibid, Miscellaneous, 1807, Box 82, folder 16.
31Ibid, Miscellaneous, Box 83, folder 13. Additional materials on this case are located in Summons for Evidence, Box 85, folders 13-15,
32Ibid, Miscellaneous, Box 83, folders 16, 18, 20, and 25.
33Ibid, Partition of Lands, 1749, Box 84, folder 2.
34Index of Revolutionary War Pension Applications in the National Archives, Bicentennial Edition (Revised & Enlarged), (Washington, D.C.: National Genealogical Society, 1976), x.
35A handful of additional pension applications can be found in the records of the New London Justice of the Peace and City Court and in Revolutionary War Pensions series of New London County, Superior Court, Papers by Subject.
36Papers by Subject, Pensions, Revolutionary War, Taylor, Elijah, Box 85, folder 5.
37The series also includes of related documents, like occasional correspondence, depositions, jury verdicts, petitions, pleadings, presentments, and testimonies.
38Papers by Subject, Summons for Evidence, 1700, Box 85, folder 8.
39Ibid, 1718, Summons for Evidence, Box 85, folder 16.
40Ibid, 1725, Summons for Evidence, Box 86, folder 8.
41Ibid, 1728, Summons for Evidence, Box 86, folder 17.
42Ibid, Travel, 1726, Box 91, folder 17.
43Ibid, Travel, 1753 Jun, Box 92, folder 25.
44Ibid, Travel, 1844 Feb, Box 103, folder 5.
45Frederic J. Wood, The Turnpikes of New England (Boston: Marshal Jones Company, 1919), 334-35.
46Also included is one March 1820 financial statement from the Stonington Bridge Lottery. Papers by Subject, Travel, Box 99, folder 10.
Related Material
As indicated earlier, Papers by Subjects consists of materials divided among eighteen subjects removed from Trials after the Connecticut State Library acquired these records in 1921. In some instances, like Admissions to the Bar, Conservators and Guardians, Jurors, Licenses, Pensions, Revolutionary War, and Travel, these divisions expedite research, but for such subjects as Costs, Executions, and Summons for Evidence these removals inhibit research by separating materials that belong together.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. County Court (New London County)
Subjects:
County courts -- Connecticut -- New London County -- History; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; Connecticut. County Court (New London County) -- History; Connecticut. Judicial Dept. -- History
Document Types:
Civil court records; Criminal Court records; Judicial records
Restrictions on Access
All records in Papers by Subject are freely accessible to researchers. As with Files, however, all original documents relating to African Americans and Native Americans have been removed and photocopied. One photocopy has been inserted in Papers by Subject at the location of the original and the second copy has been placed in the New London County African Americans Collection or New London County Native Americans Collection.
See the policy.
Provenance
Papers by Subject came to the Connecticut State Library in 1921 with the rest of the records of the New London County Court, 1666-1855.
Container List
- 1. Admissions, 1768-1855
  - Admissions (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
- 2. Appointments of Officers, 1781-1855
  - Appointments
    - 1781 - 1825 (Box 1, Folder 11-20)
    - 1826 - 1855 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
- 3. Confiscated Estates and Loyalists, 1781-1782
  - Confiscated Estates (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 4. Conservators and Guardians, 1706-1845
  - Allyn - Bolles (Box 2, Folder 11-19)
  - Breed - Cushing (Box 3, Folder 1-22)
  - Davis - Jerome (Box 4, Folder 1-19)
  - Johnson - Mott (Box 5, Folder 1-18)
  - Niles - Tyler (Box 6, Folder 1-18)
  - Walbridge - Young (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
- 5. Costs, 1693-1855
  - 1693 - 1712 November (Box 7, Folder 8-21)
  - 1713 June - 1718 November (Box 8, Folder 1-19)
  - 1719 June - 1722 November (Box 9, Folder 1-19)
  - 1723 February - 1725 November (Box 10, Folder 1-20)
  - 1726 February - 1729 November (Box 11, Folder 1-20)
  - 1730 February - 1732 November (Box 12, Folder 1-23)
  - 1733 February - 1735 November (Box 13, Folder 1-22)
  - 1736 June - 1738 February (Box 14, Folder 1-27)
  - 1738 February - 1739 November (Box 15, Folder 1-20)
  - 1740 February - 1742 November (Box 16, Folder 1-20)
  - 1743 February - 1748 November (Box 17, Folder 1-19)
  - 1749 February - 1752 November (Box 18, Folder 1-17)
  - 1753 February - 1757 November (Box 19, Folder 1-20)
  - 1758 February - 1761 November (Box 20, Folder 1-17)
  - 1762 February - 1763 November (Box 21, Folder 1-15)
  - 1764 February - 1766 November (Box 22, Folder 1-19)
  - 1767 February - 1770 November (Box 23, Folder 1-18)
  - 1771 February - 1812 (Box 24, Folder 1-20)
  - 1813 - 1838 (Box 25, Folder 1-20)
  - 1838 - 1855, undated (Box 26, Folder 1-10)
- 6. Court Expenses, 1700-1847
  - Expenses (Box 26, Folder 11-23)
- 7. Executions, 1700-1855
  - 1700 - 1720 (Box 27)
    - A - O (Box 27, Folder 1-18)
    - P - Y (Box 28, Folder 1-10)
  - 1721 - 1725 (Box 28)
    - A - F (Box 28, Folder 11-18)
    - G - Y (Box 29, Folder 1-17)
  - 1726 - 1729 (Box 29)
    - A (Box 29, Folder 18-19)
    - B - L (Box 30, Folder 1-19)
    - M - W (Box 31, Folder 1-17)
  - 1730 - 1734 (Box 31)
    - A - B (Box 31, Folder 18-20)
    - C - P (Box 32, Folder 1-20)
    - O - W (Box 33, Folder 1-14)
  - 1735 - 1739 (Box 33)
    - A (Box 33, Folder 15-17)
    - B - F (Box 34, Folder 1-20)
    - G - M (Box 35, Folder 1-20)
    - N - V (Box 36, Folder 1-18)
    - W - Y (Box 37, Folder 1-4)
  - 1740 - 1744 (Box 37)
    - A - F (Box 37, Folder 5-20)
    - G - O (Box 38, Folder 1-19)
    - P - Y (Box 39, Folder 1-20)
  - 1745 - 1749
    - A - Y (Box 40, Folder 1-19)
  - 1750 - 1759
    - A - G (Box 41, Folder 1-18)
    - H - S (Box 42, Folder 1-22)
    - T - Y (Box 43, Folder 1-7)
  - 1760 - 1764 (Box 43)
    - A - B (Box 43, Folder 8-19)
    - C - G (Box 44, Folder 1-21)
    - H - M (Box 45, Folder 1-21)
    - N - Y (Box 46, Folder 1-30)
  - 1765 - 1773
    - A - D (Box 47, Folder 1-20)
    - E - L (Box 48, Folder 1-21)
    - M - R (Box 49, Folder 1-21)
    - S - Y (Box 50, Folder 1-15)
  - 1781 - 1789 (Box 50)
    - A (Box 50, Folder 16-18)
    - B - D (Box 51, Folder 1-22)
    - E - J (Box 52, Folder 1-20)
    - K - O (Box 53, Folder 1-18)
    - P - T (Box 54, Folder 1-22)
    - U - Y (Box 55, Folder 1-12)
  - 1790 - 1799 (Box 55)
    - A - C (Box 55, Folder 13-22)
    - D - M (Box 56, Folder 1-20)
    - N - W (Box 57, Folder 1-14)
  - 1800 - 1810 (Box 57)
    - A - B (Box 57, Folder 15-22)
    - C - J (Box 58, Folder 1-20)
    - K - S (Box 59, Folder 1-19)
    - T - Y (Box 60, Folder 1-9)
  - 1811 - 1820 (Box 60)
    - A - B (Box 60, Folder 10-18)
    - C - K (Box 61, Folder 1-18)
    - L - V (Box 62, Folder 1-18)
    - W - Y (Box 63, Folder 1-7)
  - 1820 - 1829 (Box 63)
    - A - C (Box 63, Folder 8-20)
    - D - M (Box 64, Folder 1-21)
    - N - W (Box 65, Folder 1-20)
  - 1830 - 1839
    - A - Fa (Box 66, Folder 1-18)
    - Fe - Ma (Box 67, Folder 1-17)
    - Me - Wa (Box 68, Folder 1-18)
    - We - Y (Box 69, Folder 1-7)
  - 1840 - 1850 (Box 69)
    - A - D (Box 69, Folder 8-19)
    - E - Me (Box 70, Folder 1-20)
    - Mi - Tha (Box 71, Folder 1-20)
    - Tho - Y (Box 72, Folder 1-7)
  - 1851 - 1855 (Box 72)
    - A - W (Box 72, Folder 8-18)
- 8. Inquests, 1711-1840
  - Inquests (Box 72, Folder 19)
- 9. Insolvents, 1756, 1800
  - Insolvents (Box 72, Folder 20)
- 10. Jurors, 1700-1855
  - Bozrah, 1787 - 1844 (Box 73, Folder 1-6)
  - Canterbury, 1714, 1716 (Box 73, Folder 7)
  - Colchester, 1784 - 1844 (Box 73, Folder 8-13)
  - East Lyme, 1840 - 1844 (Box 73, Folder 14)
  - Franklin, 1787 - 1844 (Box 73, Folder 15-21)
  - Griswold, 1816 - 1844 (Box 73, Folder 22-24)
  - Groton (Box 73)
    - 1711 - 1735 (Box 73, Folder 25-26)
    - 1736 - 1844 (Box 74, Folder 1-10)
  - Killingly, 1714 (Box 74, Folder 11)
  - Killingworth, 1714, 1745 - 1785 (Box 74, Folder 11)
  - Lebanon, 1714 - 1720, 1824 - 1844 (Box 74, Folder 12-13)
  - Ledyard, 1837 - 1844 (Box 74, Folder 14)
  - Lisbon, 1787 - 1844 (Box 74, Folder 15-18)
  - Lyme (Box 74)
    - 1713 - 1735 (Box 74, Folder 19-20)
    - 1736 - 1844 (Box 75, Folder 1-10)
  - Montville, 1787 - 1844 (Box 75, Folder 11-15)
  - New London (Box 75)
    - 1700 - 1799 (Box 75, Folder 16-21)
    - 1800 - 1844 (Box 76, Folder 1-4)
  - New London County, 1704 - 1855 (Box 76, Folder 5-18)
  - North Stonington (Box 76)
    - 1807 - 1830 (Box 76, Folder 19-20)
    - 1831 - 1844 (Box 77, Folder 1-2)
  - Norwich, 1700 - 1844 (Box 77, Folder 3-14)
  - Plainfield, 1714 - 1717 (Box 77, Folder 15)
  - Pomfret, 1714 (Box 77, Folder 15)
  - Preston (Box 77)
    - 1714 - 1800 (Box 77, Folder 16-20)
    - 1801 - 1844 (Box 78, Folder 1-4)
  - Salem, 1820 - 1844 (Box 78, Folder 5-7)
  - Saybrook, 1700 - 1785 (Box 78, Folder 8-11)
  - Stonington (Box 78)
    - 1700 - 1809 (Box 78, Folder 12-20)
    - 1810 - 1844 (Box 79, Folder 1-3)
  - Waterford, 1802 - 1844 (Box 79, Folder 4-7)
  - Bozrah, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 8)
  - Colchester, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 9)
  - East Lyme, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 10)
  - Franklin, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 11)
  - Griswold, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 12)
  - Groton, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 13)
  - Lebanon, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 14)
  - Ledyard, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 15)
  - Lisbon, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 16)
  - Lyme, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 17)
  - Montville, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 18)
  - New London, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 19)
  - North Stonington, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 20)
  - Norwich, 1845 - 1855 (Box 79, Folder 21)
  - Preston, 1845 - 1855 (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - Salem, 1845 - 1855 (Box 80, Folder 2)
  - Stonington, 1845 - 1855 (Box 80, Folder 3)
  - Waterford, 1845 - 1855 (Box 80, Folder 4)
- 11. Licenses, 1702-1855
  - A - Le (Box 80, Folder 5-21)
  - Lo - Y (Box 81, Folder 1-14)
- 12. Meeting House, 1730-1817
  - Chelsea/New Chelsea (Norwich), 1759 - 1794 (Box 81, Folder 15)
  - Chesterfield, 1770 - 1773 (Box 81, Folder 16)
  - Groton, 1761 - 1767 (Box 81, Folder 17)
  - Lyme (Box 81)
    - First Society, 1764, 1815 (Box 81, Folder 18)
    - Third Society, 1813 (Box 81, Folder 18)
  - New Concord (Norwich), 1770, 1773 (Box 81, Folder 19)
  - Newent (Norwich), 1759 - 1771 (Box 81, Folder 20)
  - New London, North Parish, 1770 - 1772 (Box 81, Folder 20)
  - North Stonington, 1817 (Box 81, Folder 20)
  - Norwich (Box 81)
    - First Society, 1801 (Box 81, Folder 20)
    - West Society, 1749 (Box 81, Folder 20)
  - Preston
    - First Society, 1805 (Box 82, Folder 1)
    - North Society, 1767 - 1768 (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - Salem/New Salem, 1789 (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - Dissenters, 1730 - 1765 (Box 82, Folder 2)
- 13. Militia, 1709-1834
  - Militia (Box 82, Folder 3)
- 14. Miscellaneous, 1685-1856
  - Burying Ground Stonington, 1849 - 1850 (Box 82, Folder 4)
  - Common Fields, 1713 - 1749 (Box 82, Folder 5)
  - Counterfeiter's Oath, 1811 (Box 82, Folder 6)
  - Counterfeit bill of credit from Massachusetts, undated (Box 82, Folder 6)
  - County Court, 1741 - 1836 (Box 82, Folder 7)
  - Court House, 1724 - 1811 (Box 82, Folder 8)
  - Court of Common Pleas, Writs of Attachment, 1787 - 1789 (Box 82, Folder 9)
  - Estate Papers, 1699 - 1711 (Box 82, Folder 10)
  - Fishing, 1719 - 1763 (Box 82, Folder 11-12)
  - Gaol/Jail, 1715 - 1836 (Box 82, Folder 13-19)
  - James Rogers and Samuel Beebe, 1688 - 1711 (Box 83, Folder 1-2)
  - Joseph Rogers, estate of, 1700 - 1706 (Box 83, Folder 3)
  - Joan (Slave), 1711 - 1718 (Box 83, Folder 4)
  - James Rogers and Collins and William Gorton, 1776 - 1778 (Box 83, Folder 5)
  - Kirby, John, estate of, 1705 - 1707 (Box 83, Folder 6-8)
  - Lottery, 1810 - 1811 (Box 83, Folder 9)
  - Newport Mercury, 1764 January 2 (Box 83, Folder 10)
  - Power of Attorney, 1706, 1741 (Box 83, Folder 11)
  - Resolution on deaths, 1845 (Box 83, Folder 12)
  - Sanders v. Chadwick and Tillitson, 1715 (Box 83, Folder 13)
  - Schedules of court cases, 1737 - 1774 (Box 83, Folder 14)
  - Verdicts and court dockets, 1832 - 1833 (Box 83, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1685 - 1856, undated (Box 83, Folder 16-27)
- 15. Partition of Lands, 1745-1832
  - Partition of lands (Box 84, Folder 1-4)
- 16. Pensions, Revolutionary War, 1820-1853
  - A - P (Box 84, Folder 5-20)
  - Q - W (Box 85, Folder 1-7)
- 17. Summons for Evidence, 1700-1768
  - 1700 - 1722 (Box 85, Folder 8-21)
  - 1722 - 1730 (Box 86, Folder 1-21)
  - 1731 - 1739 (Box 87, Folder 1-22)
  - 1740 - 1749 (Box 88, Folder 1-22)
  - 1750 - 1757 (Box 89, Folder 1-21)
  - 1758 - 1765 (Box 90, Folder 1-21)
  - 1766 - 1768 (Box 91, Folder 1-6)
- 18. Travel, 1698-1855
  - 1698 - 1729 (Box 91, Folder 7-20)
  - 1730 - 1753 February (Box 92, Folder 1-25)
  - 1753 February - 1766 (Box 93, Folder 1-24)
  - 1767 - 1774 June (Box 94, Folder 1-26)
  - 1774 June - 1798 June (Box 95, Folder 1-22)
  - 1798 December - 1805 June (Box 96, Folder 1-22)
  - 1805 June - 1811 June (Box 97, Folder 1-24)
  - 1811 December - 1817 (Box 98, Folder 1-21)
  - 1818 - 1823 March (Box 99, Folder 1-23)
  - 1823 June - 1829 March (Box 100, Folder 1-23)
  - 1829 June - 1834 (Box 101, Folder 1-22)
  - 1835 - 1842 June (Box 102, Folder 1-24)
  - 1842 November - 1852 February (Box 103, Folder 1-23)
  - 1852 June - 1855 June (Box 104, Folder 1-9)